<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iust mans memoriall Cuius memoria in benedictionibus. To the pretious and immortall memory of the Right Honourable and truely noble Lord, William Earle of Pembroke. As it was deliuered in a sermon at Baynards Castle, before the interment of the body.</title>
            <author>Chaffinge, Thomas, ca. 1581-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107940</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843632</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843632</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1131:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iust mans memoriall Cuius memoria in benedictionibus. To the pretious and immortall memory of the Right Honourable and truely noble Lord, William Earle of Pembroke. As it was deliuered in a sermon at Baynards Castle, before the interment of the body.</title>
                  <author>Chaffinge, Thomas, ca. 1581-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Elizabeth Allde, for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.C., i.e. Thomas Chaffinge.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pembroke, William Herbert, --  3d Earl of, 1580-1630 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IVST MANS MEMORIALL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CVIVS MEMORIA JN BENEDICTIONIBVS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TO THE PRETIOVS AND IMMORTALL MEMORY OF the Right Honourable and truely Noble Lord, WILLIAM Earle of PEMBROKE: AS IT WAS DELIVERED in a Sermon at BAYNARDS Caſtle, before the Interment of the body.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Elizabeth Allde,</hi> for <hi>Nahaniel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tter. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dom.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8377:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8377:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND moſt Noble, <hi>Philip</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> and <hi>Montgomery,</hi> Lord Chamberlaine of his Maieſties Houſehold.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My very good Lord:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is the vſuall faſhion and cuſtome among vs that be Preachers, (and 'tis as commendable as common) to commit our thoughts to the ſafe cuſtody of Paper, that they may not die; and vpon occaſion, from the Paper, to award them to the Preſle, that the dead may liue. This faſhion haue I followed, and yet tis my firſt aduenture this way; and as my aduenture, ſo my mis-hap; that with <hi>Craſſus</hi> Sonne, I ſhould ſtand dumbe all my life long, till now that I haue ſeene my Gracious Maſter ſtrucke dead before mine eyes, and with <hi>Eliſha</hi> forſt to cry out after him; <hi>My Maſter, My Maſter, the Chariots of</hi> Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, <hi>and the Horſemen thereof.</hi> Time I ſee is enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and her Sickle ſo ſharpe, and keene, that it threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens
<pb facs="tcp:8377:3"/> ruine, not onely to the being and life of man, but his Memory alſo. This was it that made me put on; if not to raiſe and reuiue the one, yet at leaſtwiſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what longer to propagate the other.</p>
            <p>They be the fluctuant and wandring excurſions of a few broken, and interrupted houres; ſome of theſe <hi>herbae agreſtes,</hi> wilde herbs of the common Field, which with the Child of the Prophet, I humbly tender to your Honours hands, and make bold to ſtrow on your Noble Brothers Hearſe! I well hop'd ere this, to haue ſeene ſome fairer and ſweeter floures preſented from his owne Garden, ſuch as might haue drown'd the odour of theſe; but I perceiue ſome haue learn'd (with <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> Schollers) as well to be ſilent, as to ſpeake. <hi>Nec vox, nec verba ſuperſunt.</hi> I am ſorry to ſee the world as full now of Ingratitude, as 'twas once of Infidelity: but 'tis neither wonderfull, nor new, that though many Leapers were cleanſed, yet but one ſhould returne to giue thanks.</p>
            <p>For my part, my friends will conceiue perhaps, that as he with the very feare, leſt he ſhould breake a Chryſtall glaſſe, brake it:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frangere dum metuit, frangit Chryſtallina:</hi> So I (the leaſt of all the leaſt, <hi>Minimorum minimus,</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes) may be iudg'd to haue ſhipwrackt that ſmall credit I haue with the Liuing, out of feare to be thought vnthankefull to the Dead. But herein I bid adieu to all theſe reſpects; none of theſe things moue me, as counting nothing deare to me,<note place="margin">Acts 20.24.</note> no not mine owne life, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, that in any wiſe, I might be hold ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the bleeding memory of my deare, deare Maſter.</p>
            <p>I know none fitter to owne any Remainder of a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then a Brother, the ſole Inheritor as of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb facs="tcp:8377:3"/> ſo of his Fortunes; Let me craue then, if not your patience to read, yet your acceptance to receiue theſe poore weake lines, deuoted to his neuer-dying Memory. I haue entitled it, His Memoriall; that if any things in him were honeſt, if any things iuſt, if any things pure,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.8, 9.</note> if any things louely, if any things of good report, (as many ſuch there were) in remembring Him, you may not forget to thinke on them! In Gods name, thoſe good things which you haue both learned, and receiued, and heard, and ſeene in him, thoſe doe; and the God of bleſsing and peace ſhall be euer with you.</p>
            <p>My Lord, let me take the boldneſſe to tell you, that the eyes of the World are faſtned on you; you cannot bee hid, your actions are not done in a corner, notice will be taken of all your Counſels, and your Counſellors, men are big with the expectation of you; and blame them not that they ſhould be ſo, eſpecially of you, who (beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of your Illuſtrious Stocke and Linage well known) haue had ſo pious and religious an <hi>Aeneas</hi> to your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo famous and valiant a <hi>Hector</hi> to your Vnckle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et Frater Aeneas, &amp; Avunculus excitet:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Fiety and goodnes of the one, and the valour and Cheualry of the other, ſerue as ſo many ſiluer Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in your eares, to awaken you to all Honourable and Noble atchieuements. <hi>Miltiades</hi> Trophees would not let <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſleepe. Neither let the matchleſſe Trophees and Monuments of their glory, ſuffer your eyes to ſleepe, or your eye-lids to ſlumber: but bee rather as ſpurres to ſet you forward in the couragious proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all good cauſes for Gods Glory and the Church. O bee not idle in the Imitation of them, whoſe Image you not onely beare, but whoſe part alſo you are; ſo ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:8377:4"/> not After-ages in the Stor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of their glorious Annals, ſhut vp yours, with a <hi>Degenerem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Neoptolemum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You liue in the face of a glorious Court, where your eyes, are daily fill'd, as with Magnificence, ſo with Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; yet you ſhall doe well, otherwiſe, to caſt them aſide from ſuch Gorgeous Spectacles, and ſticke them in the ſhrowds and winding-ſheetes of the dead. Nothing ſhall more humble you then this, and ſo nothing lift you neerer Heauen then this! We vſe aſhes for the cleanſing of our Garments and doubtleſſe there is nothing better to cleanſe the ſoule from ſinne, then a frequent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation on the aſhes of our Predeceſſors. For if wee ſift theſe aſhes well, we ſhall beat them into duſt, and from duſt boult them into that nothing, out of which we were all at firſt taken. By remembring our beginning, wee ſhall ſeldome doe amiſſe: but by remembring our latter end, neuer, if the Wiſe-man ſay true. <hi>Dauid</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one day in Gods Court better then a thouſand other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; and ſurely (my Lord) you will one day find, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your death-bed, one houre ſpent in Gods ſeruice this way, more worth then ten thouſand, worne out, in empty and indefinite agitations. None is your Peere now, but your Peere; yet the time ſhall come, when you and I ſhall be fellowes; in the common bag of mortality, the Rooke is Checke-mate with the King.</p>
            <p>Therefore, among thoſe multitudes, and throngs of employments that ſtuffe the ſoule with diſtractions, and wherewithall men of your Place are often taken vp: I pray leaue one void corner, for this wholeſome thought of your Mortality; that you alſo ſhall die, ſuddenly it may be, as he hath done before you; certainely, it muſt be, as all haue, and ſhall doe hereafter. Though they be eſteemed happy that ſtand before Kings, (and ſuch hath
<pb facs="tcp:8377:4"/> your happineſſe beene to ſtand in fauour, before two moſt mighty Monarks,) to heare and obſerue their ſayings and actions, as the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſaid: yet let me put you in mind of a greater happines then this; and that is, at the laſt Day, to ſtand <hi>(rectus in Curia)</hi> before the King of Kings. O, bee as ſtudious of this, as you are of that! You goe in and out before a moſt Religious and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne, ſuch as the Sunne hath ſeldome ſeene his like! yet that you may ſee the weakenes of all earthly dependances, the Spirit of God whiſpers you in the eare, with, Truſt not in Princes, nor in any Child of Man; they may leaue you, or you them, ere you be aware. The Theaters and Scaffolds of the greateſt eminency, whereon you great Petentates, and Grandees act your ſeuerall parts, either ſtand leaning and reeling on the quick-ſand of Mutability, and Inconſtancie, or elſe lie open and obnoxious to the wind of Disfauour, and Diſgrace.</p>
            <p>It is the Staffe and Rod of Gods feare and obedience that muſt ſuſtaine you, when happely the Staffe of your Honour, like that of <hi>Egypt,</hi> may breake, and runne into your hand. If your Counſell be of God, (as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſaid) if you make him your foundation, aſſure your ſelfe, your Houſe ſhall ſtand, you ſhall ſee your Childrens Children, and peace vpon <hi>Iſrael.</hi> If you miſſe of your Ground-worke here, you can expect nothing but ruine; <hi>Tectum</hi> will be <hi>Sepulchrum,</hi> your Houſe ſhall bee your Graue, as that was to <hi>Samſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As at firſt I crau'd your patience to accept; ſo now I ſue for pardon to acquit my ouer-great preſumption with your Lordſhip; As the Nouelliſts ſaid of ſome ſhort eiaculatory Praiers in our Liturgie, that they were rather good wiſhes, then Praiers; My deſire is, I ſhould be ſo vnderſtood of your Honour, as if my counſell were
<pb facs="tcp:8377:5"/> rather taken for direction, then inſtruction, and for my honeſt well-wiſhing, to your Houſe, and Family, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my bold aduice. The God of all bleſsing continue his Bleſsings towards you, and multiply his Graces on you, and yours, your Honourable Lady, with the reſt of your moſt hopefull Poſterity, to the Worlds end.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, in all reſpects, moſt dutifully oblig'd, <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8377:5"/>
            <head>THE IVST MANS MEMORIALL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ESAY 57.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and Mercifull men are taken away, none conſidering that the Righteous is taken away from the euill to come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> may goe for a Prophetical Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, or an Euangelical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; ſome of vs haue heard to bee the ſpeach of S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome;</hi> that he was a Prophet euen in this, that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous periſheth. O that we could! we cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but for an Euangeliſt, whatſoeuer he was to the righteous man, ſure I am, he was none to vs. <hi>Euangelium</hi> is glad tidings, good newes. This that I haue now deliuered, ſad and heauy, I may
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8377:6"/> ſafely ſay, though in another ſenſe, that which old <hi>Eli</hi> ſaid, 'Tis no good newes; 'Tis no good meſſage that we heare.</p>
            <p>But ſorrow had almoſt made me forget what I had to ſay; I haue laid my Sceane in <hi>Iury,</hi> and thither I muſt againe, and begin my Sermon where <hi>Eſay</hi> ended his. And I doe not miſcall it, when I ſay a Sermon, for 'tis a piece of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that the Prophet made, not at the Funerall of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> or <hi>Ezechiah</hi> only, (Alas for <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> Alas, his glory had beene enough for theſe) but euen of all the land of <hi>Iudea</hi> beſides; God had euen now giuen his ſignall to the battell, was now gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his Beloued into the hand of his enemies, had now ſet vp his ſtandard on high, aduanced his ſtreaming Enſignes to call for the Bee of <hi>Aſsyria,</hi> and to hiſſe for the Hornet of <hi>Babylon;</hi> his meaning was to let in a flood of Nations vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Aſſyrians, Babylonians, Grecians, Egyptians, Romanes, &amp;c. people of a ſterne countenance, and a fierce behauiour, ſpeaking a language that his people vnderſtood not, and to denounce this warre, and proclaime this iudgement is our Prophets errand, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. of the former chapter. All yee beaſts of the Field, come to deuoure, yea all yee beaſts in the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. 1. All yee beaſts and ſauage Nations. An allegory taken from the wild Boare of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and other beaſts that roote vp the Vines, and deſtroy the Vine-yards.</p>
            <p>O, but ſpare thy people, mercy cries, bleſſe thine inheritance, the ſeate of thy feete, and place where thine honor dwelleth; let not ſuch
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8377:6"/> prophane feete preſſe vpon her ſacred paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whom thou haſt choſen out of all places of the world for thine owne reſidence; here will I dwell; let not <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> be laid waſte; O be fauourable vnto <hi>Sion,</hi> rather build vp, then break downe the walls of thy <hi>Hieruſalem!</hi> But then Iudgement ſtops Mercies mouth, and her turne is to plead for God next. <hi>Verum eſt,</hi> 'Tis true ſhe ſaies, God made <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> the beauty of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and <hi>Sion</hi> the ioy of the whole earth: But, <hi>O quantum haec Niobe, &amp;c?</hi> How is ſhe degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from what ſhe was, to what ſhe is? ſhe is not ſhe now, <hi>non ſamnium in ſamnio!</hi> you cannot find <hi>Sion</hi> in <hi>Sion, Bethel</hi> is <hi>Bethauen,</hi> become and the Houſe of God, a den of theeues.</p>
            <p>The ſinnes of the Prieſts (yea, and of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Rulers too, if <hi>Caluin</hi> miſtake not, <hi>Iudices praefectos Reges</hi>) firſt cry for iudgement, and then the Peoples follow, to fill vp the meaſure of the Prieſts. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>
               </label> The ſinnes of the Prieſts are blindneſſe, ignorance, drunkenneſſe, idleneſſe, his watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are blind, they are all ignorant, they are dumbe dogs, they cannot barke. <hi>Dormientes,</hi> ſaith the vulgar; <hi>Tempori ſeruientes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">10.</note> ſaith <hi>Iu.</hi> from the Heb. Time-ſeruers well expounded, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. by looking to their own way, they all looke to their own way, euery one for his gaine, from his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Peccatum eſt ſatis,</hi> a man would thinke here were ſinnes enow, yet to theſe ſinnes they adde others as it were drunkenneſſe to thirſt, exceſſe and luxury. Come ſay they, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. we will fetch wine, &amp; we will fill our ſelues with ſtrong drink, <hi>&amp; erit ſicut hodie, ſic &amp; cras,</hi> to morrow ſhall be as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8377:7"/> this day, and much more abundantly. See the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitancy of theſe men, <hi>craſtinum peccatum hodie delinquu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> as <hi>Nyſſen</hi> of the rich man in the Goſpel, they ſin to day for to morrow, &amp; yet they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <hi>hodier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> nay, <hi>heſterni,</hi> yeſterdaies men, and not to daies, for we are no more by <hi>Dauids</hi> recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we are but of yeſterday, &amp; know nothing, for our daies paſſe away on earth, as doth a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21. Theſe be the ſins of the Princes and Prieſts.</p>
            <p>The peoples ſinnes ſucceede the Prieſts and Princes, <hi>(vt Sacerdos, ſic populus)</hi> and theirs is want of conſideration, they are all careleſſe, retch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, regardleſſe of the death of good men, of the taking away of mercifull men, they lay not this to heart, that's their ſin, &amp; 'tis the generall ſin of them al <hi>Non eſt qui recogitat, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt qui intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git,</hi> ſo one Tranſlation runnes: <hi>Nemo homo reponit in animo, nemine aduertente;</hi> ſo another: Prince, and Prieſt and people ſinne, and iuſt men, mercifull men, are taken away for their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The righteous, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We conſider in the word 3. generalls.</p>
            <p>Three things:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The generality of mortality, deaths impartiality, the righteous them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, euen the righteous, they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, they die.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Mans ſecurity, and in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all that, though the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous periſh, no man, none, not a man, very few if any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that the beſt ſpoke in their wheele is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the beſt ſtake in their hedge
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8377:7"/> plucked vp, the faireſt flowre in their garden withered, none conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this, none layes this to heart.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Behold the ſeuerity and bounty of God, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks; his iudgement and his mercy going hand in hand ſeuerity and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them that are left, bounty and mercy to them that are taken away: They are taken away from the euill to come.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the Prophet complaines of this generality of neglect and diſregard, 'twere good we had an eye backe to euery one of theſe three, as we goe along. Firſt, a glaunce, a regard to this generality of mortality, conſider that; lay that to heart; Secondly, a glaunce on the generality of this diſreſpect, and neglect, conſider that, &amp;c. Thirdly, one eye on Gods ſeuerity towards the ſuruiuors, they are kept and preſerued for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill day, they are left in the middeſt of a ſea of dangers; and t'other eye on Gods goodneſſe &amp; bounty towards them that are dead, they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the euill to come: one is left, for t'other is taken from the euill to come.</p>
            <p>I muſt craue pardon, if, by reaſon of mine own indiſpoſition of body and mind at this time, with the Lillies of the field, I neither labour much, nor ſpin, for what I ſhall ſay: the plaineſt and courſeſt ſtuffe is fitteſt for mourners, you know, <hi>quorum nos primi,</hi> among whom moſt of vs, I am ſure, may be chiefe, eſpecially if we ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider, if we lay to heart what our loſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8377:8"/> is, ſuch a man, ſuch a maſter; ſuch a no ſuch man, ſuch a no ſuch maſter.</p>
            <q>Priſcaparem neſcijt, aequalem poſtera nullum exhibitura dies.</q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But I betake me to my Theame, and the firſt Generall is the generality, &amp;c. of mortality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuſtus perit;</hi> There be thoſe who by <hi>Iuſtus</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> who ſuffered ſuch a ſhamefull death, as he ſeemed to periſh, and yet ſuch was the oſcitancy and vnaduiſedneſſe of men, that few or none conſidered, that for our ſinnes was he wounded, that for our tranſgreſſions was hee broken, not his owne, that the chaſtiſement of our peace was laid on him, &amp; that by his ſtripes we were healed, &amp;c. <hi>Iuſtus perit;</hi> 1. <hi>Eſaias perit,</hi> the Iewes would haue the Prophet himſelfe to bee vnderſtood here, who is ſaid to haue beene cut in pieces with a woodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaw, by idolatrous <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes! witneſſes;</hi> and thoſe other Prophets whom he ſlew to be meant by thoſe men of mercy; and ſo the Prophet was <hi>futurae calamitatis Propheta,</hi> a true Prophet indeed: But it will not be need, I conceiue, to empale that ſenſe which the Spirit of God hath laid open, and made common; <hi>Christianus</hi> will doe as well as <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> or <hi>Eſaias;</hi> to conſter this text, euery Child of God is this Iuſt man. But then it will be demanded, Is any child of God iuſt? is any that is borne of vncleane ſeed righteous? did he charge his Angels with folly, and may a ſonne of man be iuſt? Iuſt is one ſometimes who thinks himſelfe iuſt, and is not; Certaine truſted that they were iuſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.9.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8377:8"/> Sometimes one that endeuours to liue iuſtly in his generall calling as a Chriſtian, ſo were <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> both iuſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> though not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſine querela,</hi> though <hi>non ſine culpâ; ſine crimine, non ſine peccato;</hi> ſometimes one that deales iuſtly in his particular vocation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.50.</note> ſo was, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid to be a good man, and a iuſt; Sometimes one that is iuſt and righteous by the imputation of Chriſts iuſtice, <hi>iuſtus ex fide, Rom.</hi> 1.17. Sometimes one that giueth to euery man that which is his owne, Honor to whom honor, &amp;c. And laſtly, ſometimes one that performeth iuſt workes in his owne perſon, though vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, ſo was <hi>Noah</hi> ſaid to be iuſt and righteous in his Generation, Thee onely haue I ſeene righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before me, ſaies God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1. All theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions ſaue one, may ſerue to ſpan and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the meaning of the word <hi>Iuſtus;</hi> In ſhort, iuſt either firſt <hi>comparatiuè,</hi> ſo was <hi>Noah;</hi> againe iuſt in compariſon of his ſonnes and their wiues, or iuſt abſolute in reſpect of ſincerity of heart, though nor in regard of a perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate ſanctity: But be our Iuſt man what he will, or who he will, neither his iuſtice nor integrity, nor his ſincerity can ſaue him aliue, <hi>perit; Iuſtus perit?</hi> that's pitty, me thinks; 'tis no good <hi>Syntax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is,</hi> for if <hi>iuſtus, quomodo perit?</hi> and if <hi>perit? quomodo iuſtus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, ſhall the iuſt mans labour bee in vaine in the Lord? ſhall his flittings bee numbred, and the haires of his head reckoned, and his teares bottled vp that none of them be loſt, and ſhall hee periſh? hath God made all men for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8377:9"/> nought?<note place="margin">Firſt.</note> 
               <hi>perit</hi> then 1. can be no more then <hi>prate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> &amp; that the Apoſtle pronounced of the whole frame of nature, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the figure or faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this world paſſeth away, then of man too; the Sunne and Moone, theſe alſo ſhift the Sceane euery day ouer our heads, alter the figure of their round and dance daily, and are onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant but in inconſtancy. But be it as it will with thoſe celeſtiall bodies that are aboue; ours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, are ſo ſubiect to S. <hi>Iames</hi> his <hi>parallage</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> our parallaxes, &amp; our tropicks, our turnings &amp; changings, our waxings and wanings, as that we are not the ſame men now, what we were a while agoe, nor what we ſhall be a while after! ſcarce what we are; euery moment fleeceth vs of ſomewhat; <hi>Singula de nobis anni praedantur euntes;</hi> if wee die daily, we muſt needs vary and change daily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not a minute of time that we ſpend, but ſpends a pickle, ſome duſt of ſand in the houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſſe of our life; nay, for a minute that we ſpend of time, Time ſpends a moneth of ours. <hi>Seneca</hi> tells vs, that it was a Philoſophers queſtion, If a man went downe twice in a quarter of an houre or leſſe into a Riuer, whether it were the ſame Riuer or no, into which he went downe? I may make a queſtion, If it be the ſame man as well, if the ſame that goes out, as he was comming in; ſitting and ſtanding. If I be the ſame man in the pulpit that I was in my chamber but euen now; for, <hi>Ego ipſe dum loquor mutari iſta, mutatus ſum;</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca, praeterit,</hi> then will hold good ſenſe, he paſſeth, he changeth, euen the Iuſt man paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8377:9"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>Perit:</hi> referring it to the body; for as for that, the beſt language that the Heathen gaue it, was no better then a bellowes full of wind, a bag full of dung, a bottle full of ſmoke; <hi>temporis ſpolium, fati ludibrium,</hi> the laughing ſtocke of the gods, the May-game of the deſtinies, <hi>Fortunae luſus,</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes Tennis-ball, bandied from hazard to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard; the beſt that S. <hi>Bernard</hi> giues man, is but little better, <hi>ſperma faetidum, domus ſtercorum, eſca vermium;</hi> my body decaies daily. <hi>Sicut dies mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in noctem, &amp; infantia in pueritiam, &amp; pueritia in iuuentutem;</hi> theſe ſcratch and ſcramble for the little coale of my life; 'Twill be no harme then to thinke that <hi>Iuſtus perit</hi> in this ſenſe; for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt to the earth, whence it was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though the ſoule returne to God that gaue it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Or third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>perit,</hi> that is <hi>videtur perire,</hi> like a ſhooting Star, <hi>Quae ſi non cecidit, potuit cecidiſſe videri!</hi> in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count &amp; eſtimation of the wicked worldly man, the Iuſt man ſeemes to periſh, and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The Wiſeman hath pricked the ſong of theſe prophane ones, We fooles accounted his life, i. the Righteous mans life, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. madneſſe, and his end to be without honor;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 5.</note> But they ſing out of tune; for marke how they correct them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by and by? How is he numbred among the Children of God, and his lot is among the Saints? So that this periſhing is but a periſhing in ſhew, not in truth, or a preterition, or paſſing by, rather then a periſhing; or at leaſtwiſe, 'tis but <hi>perituri,</hi> the periſhing of a body that muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; otherwiſe there's nothing that doth periſh, either of the iuſt, or vniuſt: for though death be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8377:10"/> 
               <hi>via vniuerſae carnis,</hi> yet 'tis not <hi>meta,</hi> but after death commeth iudgement.</p>
            <p>For, I pray tell me, doe thoſe that ſleepe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh? no; the Iuſt mans death is but a ſleepe; our friend <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſleepeth, ſaid our Sauiour, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.11. Doe thoſe that paſſe from one place to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other periſh? from worſe to better? no; the Iuſt mans death is but <hi>tranſitus;</hi> our Sauiour called his death ſo, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.1. Doe thoſe that are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, as in a Chariot, periſh? death is <hi>Vehicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum in pace, Luk.</hi> 2. a paſſe in peace; an entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peace, a reſting ſoftly, and ſweetly, as vpon a bed; <hi>requieſcunt in cubilibus,</hi> in the very next verſe. Doe thoſe that are looſed out of priſon periſh? death is but <hi>ſolutio ex bigis, Phil.</hi> 1.23. Bring my ſoule out of priſon, ſaith <hi>Dauid; Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam educ è carcere. i. animam è corpore,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hugo,</hi> and the gloſſe; in one word, doe thoſe that goe to a wedding periſh? I trow no; death is but <hi>iter ad nuptias,</hi> when God ſhall wipe away <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euery teare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all eyes, &amp; death ſhalbe no more, nor mourning, nor cry, nor labour, for <hi>abiêre pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> the firſt things are paſſed, i. ſinnes, and their effects of ſorrow and miſery, <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſtus perit.</hi> But how doth hee periſh? which way doth he die? Hee leaues that at large, hee ſpeakes indefinitely of the manner how, becauſe the meanes and waies be infinite; <hi>moriendi mille figurae;</hi> ſome haue a long leaſe of their life gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, euen to foure ſcore and nineteene yeeres; others haue a <hi>diem clauſit extremum</hi> ſeru'd vpon them as ſoone as euer they are borne into the world; ſome doe <hi>dimidiare dies ſuos,</hi> ſome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8377:10"/> ſcarce come halfe waies, ſome mens ſunne ſets at noone, ſome in the morning, others at night, ſome thinke themſelues to their end, <hi>(multi ad fatum venere ſuum, dum fata timent)</hi> die with very thought of heart: So did Queene <hi>Mary</hi> for the loſſe of <hi>Calice.</hi> Embowell me (ſaies ſhe) when I am dead, and you ſhall find <hi>Calice</hi> written in my heart. Some ſpeake themſelues to their end, haue died with talking; ſo did <hi>Valentinian</hi> with ſtrayning his voice againſt the <hi>Sarmatian</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors. Some read themſelues to their end, ſo did <hi>Holcot,</hi> who died of the plague as he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that very verſe, <hi>Remember thy end, and thou ſhalt neuer doe amiſſe, Eccle.</hi> 7. The changes and chances of this mortall life be infinite, yet <hi>perit</hi> is the end of all; <hi>iuſtus &amp; iniuſtus,</hi> all's one here, as the foole dieth, ſo dieth the wiſe man, as the baſe, ſo the honorable, <hi>Pauperum tabernas, regum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> turres.</hi> Death ſtalkes as ſoone, and knockes as hard at the Princes Chamber doore, as at the Ploughmans Poſterne gate, there's no auoiding this <hi>perit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All haue died, all muſt die; and can any man thinke he ſhall get that by fauour, which onely God himſelfe hath by nature, to be immortall?</p>
            <p>There haue beene thoſe who haue ſought by Art to carue the hardeſt ſtone, to diſſolue the moſt flinty and brazen Adamant, to tame and ſubdue the wildeſt beaſts, but neuer any yet found that attempted a meanes to auoide death, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, vndiſſoluable, vntameable, vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoidable death. In the auerting of other dangers, either ſtrength, or power, or counſel, or cunning,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8377:11"/> or flight, of praiers, or bribes, or ſomewhat may preuaile, but death can neither be driuen away by force, nor redeemed by money, nor auoided by flight, nor auerted by counſell, nor preuented by praiers, or teares; a deafe Iudge, an inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tyrant. A King of <hi>France,</hi> that was both rich, powerfull, and victorious, found this moſt true; for being to die, All this (ſaith he) will not obtaine the prorogation of death one houre.</p>
            <p>No; if any, or all this would haue done it, our deare Maſter that's now loſt to vs, had bene amongſt vs ſtill, and our dead Lord had beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, I had ſpared my paines from this ſad Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage to day, and you had ſpar'd your eyes, and hearts in this laſt ſeruice to his immortall Obſequies! Could either the ſtrength of the Souldier, or the counſell of the Lawyer, or the deuotion of the Diuine, or the skill of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, or the griefe of Seruants, or the duty of Schollers, or the praiers of the poore, or the teares of the Widdow and Fatherleſſe, or the loue euen of his Enemies, if hee had any, or the good wiſhes of all; if any, I ſay, or all theſe could haue kept him aliue, <hi>Serus in Celum,</hi> no man had gone later to Heauen then he, hee had died as old as euer liued any! <hi>Iuſtus perit,</hi> had beene out of date to day; <hi>Illud immortalitate dignum inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> (as <hi>Tully</hi> of <hi>Craſſus) illa humanitas, illa virtus non morte ſubitâ extincta eſſet,</hi> that ſweet and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical conuerſation of his, that Noble and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous diſpoſition, that truely Honorable and vertuous inclination had not beene extinct ſo ſuddenly; <hi>fuit hoc luctuoſum ſuis, acerbum patriae,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8377:11"/> graue bonis omnibus!</hi> it ſeemes to be pend of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for him; this hath brought diſtraction and perplexity to his Seruants, bitterneſſe to his Country; And I thinke there's no honeſt man liuing, who either had knowne him, or heard of him, but is ſorry at the heart for the death of the Earle of <hi>Pembroke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man of that ſtate and vſe, as things now ſtand, that what <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſaies of <hi>Striſſet</hi> the calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator, he was worthy, <hi>quem neque ſenium ſenem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret, neque naturae lex vitâ priuaret;</hi> neither to bee broken with age, nor ſtrucken with death. And for our parts that were his Seruants, I thinke, I may ſay that which <hi>Valerius</hi> doth of <hi>Cornelia,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the loſſe of her louing Husband, <hi>Cornelians neſcio an foeliciorem dixerim, quod talem virum habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, an miſeriorem, quod amiſerit;</hi> I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we were more happy in hauing ſuch a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or more vnhappy that we haue loſt him; <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus perit!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am loth to giue him more, then hee would haue giuen himſelfe; though I call him iuſt, yet I dare not ſay he was perfect; though righteous, yet not without ſinne: I ſhould lie, and I ſay not, <hi>non eſt humilitas,</hi> but <hi>non eſt veritas,</hi> there were no truth in me; he knew that the way to heauen by innocency was long ſithence blocked vp, and therefore he tooke another courſe, and our hope is, he is arriu'd there by the way of penitencie; hee that was ſo often, ſo daily, ſo duely, euery morning and euening vpon his knees to God, for the pardon of the ſinnes of his youth, I doubt not, and for preuenting the ſinnes of his age, did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8377:12"/> acknowledge he was a grieuous ſinner; and this confeſſion made him Iuſt. Hee acknowledged God his <hi>Alpha,</hi> and therefore I doubt not but his <hi>Omega</hi> too; He made God his God early, by his priuate deuotion, and there is no queſtion but God made him his too, by his ſecret inſpiration, in the vpſhot and euening of his dayes; Iuſt by the imputation of Chriſts Iuſtice, ſo Iuſt; Iuſt in the diſcharge of his particular Calling, as a Magiſtrate, ſo Iuſt; Iuſt in the ſincerity of his intentions, and ſimplicity of his heart, ſo Iuſt; Iuſt in indeauouring himſelfe in the duty of his generall Calling, as a Chriſtian, in praying, and hearing with all diligence, and attention; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Goſpell ſhall be preached, there this ſhall be ſpoken in memoriall of him, that the Chaplaines eye for direction, and the Chappels eare for attention, ones out, and t'others off, by <hi>Iuſtus perit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told you that <hi>Iuſtus</hi> was one, that giueth to euery man that which is his owne, <hi>ſuum cuique,</hi> he did ſo: Firſt, duty to his God, obedience to his Soueraigne, loue to his Equals, patience to Petitioners, regard to his Inferiours, affability to all; A Iuſt Chriſtian, a Iuſt Seruant, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and Iuſt Councellor, a Iuſt Peere, a Iuſt Steward, a Iuſt Maſter, a Iuſt Man! Whoſe Oxe, or whoſe Aſſe did hee euer take away, as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid? whoſe Vine-yard did he euer gape after, to wring from the Owner, by extortion or oppreſſion? Neyther the cries of oppreſſed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes, nor the ſorrowfull ſighing of Priſoners, nor the blood of Innocents, nor the wages of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8377:12"/> Hirelings, nor the poore Mans pledge, nor the ſhop-mans penny, did euer cry to heauen againſt him. Yet <hi>perit,</hi> this Iuſt good man is dead and gone.</p>
            <p>And as 'tis now, ſo 'twas euer heretofore true, what the Poet ſaid long ſithence:
<q>
                  <l>Optima prima ferè manibus rapiuntur auaris,</l>
                  <l>Implentur numeris deteriora ſuis!</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis the ambition of deſtiny to let the beſt goe firſt, and to leaue the Reffuſe for the world; the Patriarches they went before the Prophets, they ſucceeded the Patriarches, the Apoſtles the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; the noble armies of Martyrs the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, &amp; all the godly Profeſſors departed hence in Gods faith and feare, haue come after them; Thus hath the <hi>Te Deum</hi> beene ſung in all ages, but the beſt for the moſt part, euer firſt taken. <hi>Nec bonatam ſequitur, quàm bona prima fuit,</hi> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome comes the better, whether we regard the ages or perſons.</p>
            <p>Well, doe Iuſt men die? Then wee ſhall haue weeping, and wailing, and great mourning, ſuch as <hi>Rachels</hi> was, I hope; wee ſhall haue ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing of all ſides; the houſe of <hi>Leui</hi> and their wiues apart, &amp;c. then when <hi>Ioſiah</hi> is gathered to his Fathers, euery one wil take vp a bitter lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as was that of <hi>Hadadrimon,</hi> in the Valley of <hi>Megiddo,</hi> for <hi>Ioſiah;</hi> then you ſhall read no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Characters of woe in euery mans face; for who is there, but would willingly haue died, to haue ſpared the Iuſt mans life, ſuch as <hi>Ioſiah?</hi> Is it poſſible that <hi>Ioſephs</hi> feete ſhould be ground in the ſtocks, and no man ſorry, <hi>Super
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8377:13"/> contrituram Ioſephi,</hi> for the threſhing and flailing of <hi>Ioſeph?</hi> A man would thinke ſo, yet wee doe not find it ſo, for <hi>Iuſtus perit, &amp; non eſt qui recogitat:</hi> a generality of neglect and diſregard, like a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous ſcab, hath ſpred it ſelfe ouer all ſorts of men: for all that; though the Righteous periſh, none laies it to his heart, none laies his hand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his heart, none ſmites his thigh with <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and askes either <hi>quid feci?</hi> or, <hi>quid patres fecerunt?</hi> or, <hi>Iuſtus quid fecit?</hi> that he ſhould periſh? None conſiders that a day is comming, wherein hee ſhal either be acquitted in the merits of a Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, by an Enqueſt of Saints and Angels, or be condemned in the ſins of his Fathers; As God doth in a manner powder and brine vp the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of wicked men, as he did <hi>Lots</hi> wife, ſuffers their quarters (as it were) to be ſet vp in Stories, <hi>vt poena impij, ſit eruditio Iuſti,</hi> &amp; that <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta</hi> might bee <hi>Monimenta,</hi> their Monuments, good mens admoniſhments; So againe doth he ſent and embalme the memory of the Iuſt man, for other mens imitation, that as a reliſh, from <hi>Lots</hi> wiues pillar, ſo an Odor of a ſweet ſmell from <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> Oyntment might remaine to all poſterity.</p>
            <p>And yet ſee the ſequell, men are ſo ſtuft in the head, with the coldneſſe of charity, or ſo diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perd in their taſte with the fevriſh humor of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration and ſenſuality, that they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taſte the ſalt of the one, or with the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles, In vnguentorum odore currere,</hi> bee drawne or affected with the odors of th'other, none laies this to heart! God accepts neuer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8377:13"/> ſo little, if done from the heart; <hi>quod potuit fecit,</hi> ſaid our Sauiour in <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> caſe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.8. and 'twas well taken, and <hi>quod habuit dedit,</hi> in the poore Widdowes, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.44. and 'twas well accepted, God placeth not acceptation in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he accepts <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> deſire to feare him, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> ſetting his heart to ſeeke him, 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.3. the the ſeruants but preparing to doe his Maſters will, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.42, 47. <hi>Dauids</hi> but <hi>Secundum cor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> his honeſt true heart, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. This is all, when we haue no more, and yet no man can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord God his heart; none laies it out in <hi>pios v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> not ſo much for Gods ſake, as for his owne. 'Twas well fabled that our Progenitors were flints and ſtones, for euer ſithence <hi>documenta da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> we ſhew our breeding, wee proclaime our beginning; 'Twas a Rocke, out of which wee were hewne, and a Quatry of Adamant, out of which we were digg d; <hi>Iob</hi> expoſtulates with God, Is my fleſh of ſtone? and are my bones braſſe, ſaith he? Yes, holy <hi>Iob,</hi> our fleſh is ſtone, and our bones, and hearts, of Adamant and braſſe <hi>non eſt qui recogitat.</hi> Doe you remember what S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. ſuch and ſuch things haue beene reported to bee among you, <hi>&amp; vos non doluiſtis,</hi> he grieues that they did not grieue. Doe you remember what the Prophet ſaies? <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. Thou haſt ſmitten them, <hi>ſed non doluerunt,</hi> but they made light of it, they grieued not. Doe you remember what <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaies of the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard? They haue ſtrucken me, <hi>Sed non agrotaui;</hi> 'Tis our caſe for all the world; God hath ſmitten
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8377:14"/> many a good man, about vs, aboue vs, below vs, on both ſides of vs, and we haue not beene ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, either of our own blowes, or of theirs. 'Twas <hi>Verbum vigilans,</hi> haue you no regard? Is it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to you? <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.12. A ſtrange matter! Let God ſmite the Rocke, and that melts preſently into compaſſion; Let him but blow with his Fanne vpon the Seas, and the waters will roare; If he doe but touch the mountaines, they ſmoke. <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe hath eloquence enough to reproue the madnes of a Prophet; onely man is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate and indolent, hee alone of all other creatures, as if he had the Prieſt to his Father, and were a-kinne to the Leuite by the Mothers ſide, paſſes by the wounded man, the Iuſt dead man; and cannot afford him ſo much as the oyle of his eyes, in ſtead of a flower to caſt after him into his graue. Let vs all pray with the Spouſe, Blow O South wind, and thaw our fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen and congealed hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> With <hi>Ioſua</hi> beſeech the Sunne of righteouſneſſe to ſtand ſtill ouer <hi>Gibeon</hi> and <hi>Atalon,</hi> the rocky and darke valleyes of our hearts, that we may lay this to heart; that the righteous periſheth, and as it followes, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull men are taken away; and ſo I proceede.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viri miſericordiae,</hi> ſaith the vulgar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Homines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigni; Iunius,</hi> or as the <hi>Heb. benignitatis; recipiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>colliguntur</hi> ſaith another; as corne is into the barne, or as flowers are to weaue a Garland; <hi>colliguntur non rapiuntur,</hi> as the fooles ſoule was againſt his will, <hi>Exeunt iſtinc voluntatis obſequio, non neceſsitatis vinculo;</hi> mercifull men are but taken, cruell men are compelled and hal'd by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8377:14"/> violence to a fearefull end. Turne ouer the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Romane Emperours, and you ſhall hardly finde one of them that was a cruell man, a blood-ſhedder, but his blood was ſhed. <hi>Neque enim lex iuſtior vlla eſt. Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſtab'd by the hands of <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſsius. Antonius</hi> by his owne; <hi>Claudius</hi> by <hi>Caius Caligula; Caius</hi> by the Praetorian Souldiers; <hi>Nero</hi> that butcher'd the Apoſtles, at laſt became his owne executioner; <hi>Galba</hi> ſucceeds <hi>Nero, Otho</hi> ſlayes him, and ere long after, himſelfe. <hi>Vitellius</hi> comes next to <hi>Otho,</hi> who was made away too, and not vouchſafed the honor of buriall. <hi>Domitian</hi> is Succeſſor to <hi>Vitellius,</hi> and after he had baniſhed S. <hi>Iohn</hi> into <hi>Pathmos,</hi> is cruelly put to death in his own Palace;
<q>
                  <l>Ad gremium Cereris ſine caede &amp; ſanguine pauci</l>
                  <l>Deſcendunt Reges, &amp; ſiccâ morte tyranni.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Iudgement without mercy ſhall he haue that ſhewed no mercy, and mercy triumpheth ouer iudgement, &amp;c. The mercifull men are but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in, gathered vp; the mercileſſe are rent and torne by violence, to the iudgement to come: But we are ſpeaking of men of Mercy.</p>
            <p>The Mercy of a man is ſeene in three things eſpecially: 1. <hi>donando,</hi> in giuing: 2. <hi>condonando,</hi> forgiuing: 3. <hi>conſolando,</hi> comforting. The firſt, that makes <hi>virum benignum,</hi> the ſecond, <hi>bonum:</hi> but the third, <hi>virum miſericordiarum,</hi> a man made vp of mercies, ſo that a mercifull man is one that doth <hi>miſeriae condolere,</hi> and <hi>miſero ſuccurrere,</hi> grieues for the miſery of the miſerable, &amp; ſeekes to relieue the miſerable in their miſery; <hi>miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors quaſi miſerum cor habeus,</hi> ſaies the old Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſt.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8377:15"/>
            <p>There be ſome which haue no memorial, ſaith the Wiſe man, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 44.10. who are periſhed as though they had neuer beene; and are become as though they had neuer beene borne, and their children after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bell that knolls to their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, knocks out the memory of their whole life; a fearefull iudgement vpon cruell men; yet this we find by daily experience but what followes in that place? <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>Sed ſunt viri miſericordiae:</hi> but there are men of mercy, whoſe righteouſnes hath not beene forgotten, with their Poſterity ſhall remaine a good inheritance, &amp;c. Their bodies are buried in peace, but their name liueth for euermore; though <hi>Iuſtus perit</hi> bee true, yet <hi>Iuſtitia manet</hi> is as true; though they bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, yet their mercy ſhall neuer be buried in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuion; Theſe be the men of mercy. Of <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſame Author ſaies, <hi>cap.</hi> 45.1. that his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial was bleſſed, that he was beloued of God and men, that hee found fauour in the ſight of all fleſh, and all was becauſe hee was a mercifull man; the Canonicall Scripture makes him the meekeſt man vpon earth, <hi>Num.</hi> 12. and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphall, the mercifulleſt; So that if either be true, he muſt needs obtaine mercy. Bleſſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercy.</p>
            <p>And to apply this againe to our dead Maſter, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> applied his liuing body to the dead childs, it wil not be very hard. S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaies of a Preacher, <hi>Ille praedicat viuâ voce, qui praedicat vitâ &amp; voce:</hi> ſo he is truly merciful, that to the pitty of the heart addes the bounty of the hand. Hee that is dead, our gracious &amp; mercifull Maſter, <hi>(cuius me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8377:15"/> in benedictionibus)</hi> did ſo, he did <hi>alterius miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam quaſi ſuam reputare,</hi> he accounted others mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, as his owne, and that was it that made him pittifull; and he did, <hi>de malo alterius quaſi de ſuo dolere,</hi> he grieued for other mens ſorrowes, as for his owne, and that made him mercifull; He did not ſhut vp the doore of compaſſion and commiſeration from the neceſſitous, as S <hi>Iohn's</hi> phraſe is, there was his pitty: but he euen pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of his ſoule to the needy, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58. as 'tis our Prophets phraſe: There was his mercy.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Iob</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob</note> of himſelfe, that I of him, <hi>De vtero matris egreſſa mecum, ab infantiâ meâ mecum creuit miſeratio,</hi> mercy was brought vp with him from his youth, as with a Father, &amp; he guided her from his Mothers wombe, &amp; what <hi>Bernard</hi> of mercy &amp; peace, they be <hi>collectaneae,</hi> bedfellowes, they ſleepe together, &amp; <hi>collactaneae</hi> in another place, Foſter-brothers, they ſuck one milke, one breſt together, that I of him &amp; mercy; ſhe was his bedfellow fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his cradle, his foſter-ſiſter from his mothers breſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Naz.</hi> at the funerall of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> doubted not to affirme, that <hi>Athanaſium laudare,</hi> was <hi>idem ac virtutem ipſam laudare,</hi> to commend <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> was al one, as to frame a Panegyricke of vertue her ſelfe. Pardon me, if my vnfained affection and ſeruice to my dead Maſter, carry me ſo farre to ſay, that to commend this mercifull man were all one, as to commend mercy it ſelfe: A true diſciple of a bleſſed Maſter, The broken Reed did not he bruiſe, the ſmoking flaxe would not he quench. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaies, that the very mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the wicked are cruell, becauſe their kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8377:16"/> and benefits are rather beſtowed to the hurt then the good of other; All the cruelties that he had, were mercies: With good <hi>Theodoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, neminem dimiſit tristem,</hi> neuer Suitor went ſad from his preſence: though hee beg'd of his Sauiour euery day, yet he neuer beg'd of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soueraigne but once, and that not for himſelfe neither, but that the Widdow and the fatherleſſe might not beg; he had our Sauiours rule by heart, he knew 'twas <hi>regalius dare, qúàm ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere,</hi> more like a Prince to giue, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue: ſo that I may ſay, True Nobility before him went, but for a morall vertue, hee onely made it a diuine: And as <hi>Auguſtine, Epiſt.</hi> 123. of a good ſoule deceaſed, <hi>Illa quidem anima in ſocieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem fidelium &amp; caſtarum recepta, laudes nec curat, nec quaerit, humanas imitationem tantum querit.</hi> That good Soule now taken vp into the company of the faithfull Saints departed, neither regards, nor requires our commendations; all his deſire is, that we would imitate his example in this; that I of him, Goe and doe thou likewiſe. And ſhall we doubt to ſay now, as <hi>Paul</hi> doth, that hee hath found mercy already? that is the fruit of mercy; and ſhall find it in more abundance at that Day? Shall we doubt to affirme that which our Sauiour doth of the mercifull; <hi>ergà eum erunt miſerationes,</hi> as the Syriack renders it in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall? No; he hath receiued mercies for himſelfe there, and our hope is, he ſhall receiue mercies for his, here; thoſe that come after him ſhall be bleſſed, mercy for meaſure, mercy for mercy, mercy obtaind for mercy beſtowed, <hi>diſperſit &amp;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8377:16"/> dedit, dedit temporalia, accepit aeterna.</hi> He hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed abroad, and giuen to the poore: hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd to God his temporals, and God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd on him mercie for all eternity.</p>
            <p>Iuſtice could not keepe the Righteous man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, <hi>Iuſtus perit:</hi> but may not mercy, by which we neerer reſemble God then by iuſtice, preſerue the mercifull? No, neither; euen thoſe are taken away too; <hi>colliguntur,</hi> like flowres or fruits that are gathered, ripe; Till thirty we are welcome to the world, in the kindeſt manner; from that, till fifty, much good doe it vs; but from fifty forward, is a time of taking leaue, and ſo God be with vs; his time was ſo, in the yeere of his Iubile, in his fiftieth yeere, he returnes from this Land of his captiuity, to the Land of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, the Land of perfect liberty, <hi>colligitur,</hi> he is taken away, taken vp; As a Maſter from his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, as a Shepheard from his Sheepe, as a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar from a Church, as a Buttreſſe from a leaning wall, as a Guardian from his Pupils, as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome from his Bride, ſo is he taken; nay more, as a Father from his Brother, as a Brother from his friends, as a kinſman from ſtrangers, as a Friend from all; ſo is he taken away.</p>
            <p>The goodly Tree (like that in <hi>Daniel</hi>) that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorded vs ſhaddow, and meat, and drinke, and fewell, was our all, <hi>omnia Gratianus,</hi> as he in <hi>Auſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, roſtra, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uilia, caſtra, agri, domus, nummus, fundus, nobis omnia Gratianus,</hi> onely with a voice from heauen is now falne, cut downe, and taken away: now he is truely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Tree turn'd topſy-turuy, vpſide downe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8377:17"/> this can God doe; this can hee doe, that thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the clouds aboue. He that flouriſhed as the Cedar of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> not many daies agoe, lies now as low as any ſhrub of the Deſart! with one ſtroke of thunder is our Lawrell blaſted; the Tree, vnder whoſe goodly bowes wee ſported and recreated our ſelues, and vnder whoſe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow we ſate downe and ſung, is felled to make Timber for the Triumphant Church in heauen, while our houſe on earth is running to decay, onely the dew lodges vpon ſome of his bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Non deficit alter</l>
               <l>Aureus, &amp; ſimili frondeſcit virga metallo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He ſeemes to liue (as it were) multiplied in an Honorable Brother, and many a ſweet Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew; and O may the dew of Heauen ſtill lodge vpon thoſe branches; let them ſpread forth as the Vallies, as Gardens by the Riuers ſide, as the Trees of <hi>Lign-aloes</hi> which the Lord hath planted, and as Cedar trees beſides the waters, <hi>Num.</hi> 24 6. <hi>Collectus eſt,</hi> he is taken; but then let me aske, who tooke him away from vs? <hi>Quis collegu?</hi> Some en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious man ſure hath done this, as we ſlept. No, not ſo; no man, if my charity miſguide me not, I ſuppoſe there liu'd not a man, bur would haue kept him aliue if he could. Who then? was it Gods doing? <hi>Factum à Domino?</hi> 'tis true; <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid patimur, quicquid facimus, venit ab alto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sparrow falls not without his prouidence, much leſſe doe Princes and Great men fall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his leaue. But I muſt ſearch yet neerer into this, <hi>Quis colligit?</hi> Was it neither man nor God? Who then? Shall I tell you? Your ſins (our ſins,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8377:17"/> that I except not my ſelfe from the number) haue made a ſeparation betweene him and vs, and our iniquities haue hid him from vs, ſo that we ſhall ſee the face of our deare Maſter no more.</p>
            <p>Behold, ſaies God, for your iniquities haue you ſold your ſelues; and for your tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is your mother put away, in the 50. of this Propheſie, Our Maſter, ſay I, is taken away. We may well complaine of theſe, as <hi>Mary</hi> did, vpon ſhe knew not whom; <hi>Suſtulerunt Dominum,</hi> they haue taken away our Lord from vs, and we know too well to our griefe, the place where they haue laid him; <hi>Quis talia fando?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can any man then forbid teares, that we that were his Seruants, ſhould not weepe, as he ſaid of the water? Surely no, <hi>non arguo doloris affectum, ſed doledi exceſsu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> as <hi>Bleſenſis</hi> to a King of England, ſorrowing for the death of his ſonne, <hi>Conuerſus eſt planctus eius in gaudiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, conuertatur &amp; veſter: Epiſt.</hi> 107. his ſorrow is turned into ioy, let yours be ſo too. As Chriſt to the women of <hi>Hieruſalem, Nolite flere,</hi> Weepe not for me, not for thee, for whom then? weepe not ſo, ſo weepe rather for your ſelues, and the ſinnes of your owne ſoules; for though ill for vs, yet 'tis good for him: Weepe not for him therefore thus, but reſt aſſured, that if you ſerue him as you ought, what you haue loſt in him, you ſhall find in God. If thou ſeeke him, he will be found of thee, ſaies <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Salomon;</hi> he will be with you, while you be with him; As <hi>Elkanah</hi> to <hi>Hannah,</hi> Why weepeſt thou, &amp;c? Am not I better then ten ſonnes? Let the Wife ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhe heares God comforting her, Am not I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8377:18"/> better then ten Husbands? and the Brother, Am not I better then ten Brothers? and the Nephew, Am not I better then ten Vnkles? &amp; the Seruant, &amp; the Poore, Am not I better then ten Maſters? then ten Benefactors? For to ſay truth, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Comforters are all theſe; Husband, or Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Kinſman, or Maſter, or Patrone, if God himſelfe make not one. And becauſe no man laies to heart, no man conſiders the generality of mortality, or the generality of the diſregard had to the periſhing of the Iuſt, to the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of mercifull men, let vs caſt an eye that way, conſider that they doe not conſider, Be wiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, leſt we be wiſe, when it will be too late! <hi>Boterus de m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ribus gentium,</hi> ſaies, that the Italian is wiſe before-hand; the Frenchman after the thing is done, the Almaine in the doing: Let vs herein be the Italians Schollers, learne before hand to preuent that by our daily preparation, which otherwiſe will preuent vs. S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> to put thee throughly in mind of thy vanity, thy mortality, tells thee, that God hath made the earth, <hi>patriam,</hi> to teach thee, that thou art Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try man to Vanity; and <hi>nutricem,</hi> to leſſon thee, that thou art Foſter-child to Vanity; and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem,</hi> Sonne of Vanity; and <hi>Menſam,</hi> a Gueſt to Vanity; and <hi>Domum,</hi> a Tennant to Vanity; and laſtly, <hi>Sepulchrum</hi> too, the Priſoner to Vanity; like an Anchoret thou feedeſt on thy graue, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt in thy graue, ſuck'ſt on thy graue, dwelleſt in thy graue, and at laſt ſhalt be clothed with thy graue; And though thy thoughts be as ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as <hi>Ceſars,</hi> which the great Ball of the World
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8377:18"/> could not containe, yet a leſſer on the Obeliske ſhall containe thy aſhes, as it did his, and then all thy Vanity, like thy Daies, ſhall be compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a ſpan; <hi>Vniuerſa Vanitas, omnis homo,</hi> euery man is euery way, all kind of Vanity! Haue an eye to this: and that we ſhall all riſe againe to Iudgement after theſe our daies of vanity, but in a different manner, as the Egyptians and Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, <hi>vtri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mare ſunt ingreſsi, non ſimiliter egreſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> they both went down into the ſea alike, but they came not vp alike! <hi>Violae creſcunt ſicut &amp; Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nae; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Violae in odorem, Spinae in ignem:</hi> The Thornes grow, as doe the Violets, but theſe are bound vp to make a Noſe-gay, thoſe bundled vp in faggots, to make fewel for the fire. Haue one eye that way. <hi>Palmares poſuiſti dies:</hi> Thou haſt made my daies as it were a ſpan long.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſeeing 'tis ſo, that moſt men haue the leaſt regard of the Iuſt mans periſhing, &amp; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull mens taking away, let's haue another eye that way; let's grieue for them, that they grieue not for themſelues, or others; our Sauiour did ſo: <hi>O ſi cognouiſſes, &amp; tu!</hi> O that thou hadſt, &amp;c! He cannot goe thorow with his ſentence for weeping, and throbbing, <hi>Singultu medios impedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſonos.</hi> O, this is a diſeaſe too Epidemicall in the world, that the death of others, ſo ſudden ſometimes, ſo certaine alwaies, yet cannot win vs to prepare for, to beware of our owne! Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py whiles the paſſing Bell goes, or the Buriall is reading, or the Corps lies before our faces, we can be ſo deuout as to lift vp an eye or ſpend a ſigh, or beſtow a teare, or let rail a grone, or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8377:19"/> perchance at the ſame charges, a knocke vpon the breſt, with a Lord be mercifull to vs, what a fraile creature is man? to day a man, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row no man, I ſay for a very little while we are content to lend an eare to God, to conſecrate it a Sanctuary to Deuotion, and in our brothers death, to thinke vpon our owne mortality: But no ſooner is the Booke turn'd in, or the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Bell out of our eares, or the Coffin couered with earth; but wee preſently forget what we did, where we haue beene, what we haue ſeene, or heard.</p>
            <p>And inſtantly we begin to make our eares &amp; mouthes Gutters and Sincks for filthy and vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoury ſpeeches, to runne vp and downe in our eyes and hearts, graues of vncleane luſts, cages for euery filthy &amp; vnwholeſome bird; we cannot leaue our old wont: like S. <hi>Iaemes</hi> glaſſe-gazer, while we are poring into the pit, we ſee as in a glaſſe our owne frailty, and can bee content to acknowledge it, but no ſooner haue wee turn'd our backes, but wee forget immediately what our faſhion and ſhape was, and we haue vtterly throwne out of our mindes, that voice which ſpeaketh vnto vs as vnto children, ſhall I ſay? nay, rather as vnto wormes and beaſts, <hi>Terra es, &amp; in terram reuerteris,</hi> Duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt returne. I cannot fitter compare ſuch Men, then to Swine, who while one of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes is going to the blocke, they yell and cry, but no ſooner hath the knife cut his throat, but preſently theirs are ſtopt, away to their waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troughs, and wallowing in the mire againe. O
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8377:19"/> conſider this, all you that forget God, conſider that you doe not conſider, that there is an euill day comming, wherin ſuch as you ſhall be taken, as Birds in a net, as Deare in a toile, when the Iuſt and Mercifull men ſhall be preſerued from the euill to come.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>A facie malitiae collectus eſt iuſtus,</hi> Heauen is <hi>faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciculus viuentium,</hi> the bundle of life, or of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing; that's the vulgar; <hi>ante faciem ipſius mali re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur iuſtus,</hi> that's the originall; that is; for illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration ſake, <hi>ante aduentum mali,</hi> before the euill day come, and the yeeres draw nigh, ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 36.6. <hi>Eſau</hi> is ſaid to haue gone into the Country of <hi>Seir,</hi> before the face of <hi>Iacob. i.</hi> before <hi>Iacob</hi> was come. This euill here meant, is that denounced at the firſt verſe, the calling in of Forraigne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to eate vp, and to deuoure Gods people. All yee beaſts, come to deuoure, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And here I told you there were two things conſiderable, Gods Iudgement, and his Mercy; his Seuerity, and his Goodneſſe; his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on thoſe that are left, his Mercy towards them that are taken away; ill for thoſe, good for theſe; th'one happy, th'other miſerable.</p>
            <p>Now the euill to come, is two-fold, contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, or neceſſary, an euill that may be, or an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill that muſt be, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Of the firſt ſort is warre, famine, peſtilence, earth-quakes, inundations; theſe be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things that may come; of the ſecond ſort is old age, and dotage, and ſickneſſe, and at the laſt, death; and after death, Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; theſe be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things that muſt come; theſe ſhall be, will we, nill we; this is the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8377:20"/> ſad night, of which our Sauiour ſpeakes, the night co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, when no man can worke, the night of age, the night of death, the night of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when theſe nights be come, no man can worke. No man will deny but that in a darke, cold, ſtormy tempeſtuous night, he has the beſt of it that is a-bed, &amp; aſleepe, and hee the worſt, that is vp and awake: Our life here is ſuch a night, and our death in Chriſt, ſuch a bed, <hi>requieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilibus;</hi> and come my people, enter thou into thy chambers, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26. The reſt in the graue is there compared to the reſt that a man takes in his bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber: And haue not they the worſt of it, then, who are left behind?</p>
            <p>Should that anguiſh and perplexity of heart, befall thee, that befell <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> when he turn'd to the wall and wept, as if hee would haue told his tale to that which could not heare him. If <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> pangs ſhould come vpon thee, or <hi>Elias</hi> trauels ouertake thee; Take away my life, why ſhould I liue? I am no better then my Fathers; Would'ſt thou not with the Wiſe man praiſe the dead, which are already dead, more then the liuing, which are yet aliue? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.2? Nay, would'ſt thou not with the foole,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.</note> eſteeme an handfull of quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in thy graue? <hi>(melior est plena vola quietis, ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis pugnis moleſtiae)</hi> better then both the hands full of trauaile and vexation of ſpirit here on earth? This is no more then that which may bee, this is an euill that may come, ere thou be aware of it. Should the caſe ſo ſtand with thee, as <hi>Moſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. when in the morning thou ſhalt ſay, Would God it were euening, &amp; in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8377:20"/> euening thou ſhalt ſay, would God it were mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c. for the feare of thy heart, wherewith thou ſhalt feare, and for the ſight of thine eyes, that thou ſhalt ſee, when thy life ſhall hang be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, like <hi>Tantalus</hi> apples, but thou ſhalt not enioy it, but rather like <hi>Diues</hi> in hell ſhalt ſee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men happy, and thy ſelfe miſerable. This is no more then that which may be, this is <hi>malum venturum,</hi> an euill to come.</p>
            <p>To come a little neerer home; Should things fall out ſo? (which yet God forbid) that though the City cried out of her gates to the Country, as the man did to <hi>Paul,</hi> Come out of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> &amp; help vs in the City, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.9. and the Country ſhould call from her ſuburbs and graunges, to the City, For the loue of God, lend vs your hand in the City, and helpe vs in the Country; Should there fall out to bee ſuch a viciſſitude of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints betweene them, and yet the City neither able to ſupply the Country with her ſweetneſſe, nor the Country the City with her fatneſſe, for feare of <hi>Mors in ollâ,</hi> bitterneſſe in the end? Who would not ſay that this were <hi>Malum venturum</hi> with a witneſſe? And yet euen ſuch an euill to come, is now feard of the wiſeſt; The thing that hath beene, it is that which ſhall be, ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and that which is done, is that which ſhall be done,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.9.</note> and there is no new thing vnder the Sunne, not in <hi>ſpecie,</hi> but hath beene done in one kind or other before we were borne; and may be againe, when we are dead, <hi>cuiuis poteſt accidere, quod cuiquam poteſt,</hi> that may happen to any one, which hath yet happened but to one.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:8377:21"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And as this ſhewes Gods Iudgement to thoſe that are left aliue, ſo his goodnes to thoſe that are taken away. Thus dealt God with <hi>Enoch,</hi> he was tranſlated, yea ſpeedily was he taken away, leſt that wickedneſſe ſhould alter his vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 4.10, 11.</note> or deceit, beguile his ſoule. <hi>A facie malitiae,</hi> thus with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.15.</note> Thou ſhalt go to thy Fathers in peace, thou ſhalt be buried in a good old age. This was Gods goodneſſe vnto <hi>Abraham.</hi> Thus with <hi>Noah,</hi> whom God tooke in the time of wrath, in exchange for the world, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 44.17. they drownd, he ſau'd. The ſame to <hi>Ezechiah</hi> by <hi>Iſaias</hi> the Prophet Behold, the daies come, when of thy ſonnes which iſſue from thee, which thou ſhalt beget, ſhall they take away, and they ſhall be Eunuches,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 20.18.</note> in the Palace of the King of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon:</hi> but as for thy part, thou ſhalt ſleepe with thy Fathers. Was not this Word of the Lord, good for <hi>Ezechiah?</hi> The like was promiſed to <hi>Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> I will gather thee vnto thy Fathers, and thou ſhalt bee gathered into thy graue in peace, and thine eyes ſhall not ſee all the euill that I will bring vpon this place.<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 22.20.</note> A great fauour to <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that this euill ſhould not come to paſſe in his time.</p>
            <p>This goodneſſe of God will appeare the more clearely, if we conſider the company which the godly part from, and the ſociety they goe to; they part from a valley of teares, from the midſt of a froward and crooked Generation. It made <hi>Dauid</hi> ſigh deepely, <hi>Hei mihi quia incolatus meus, &amp;c.</hi> Woe is me that I am conſtrained, &amp;c. They goe to an innumerable company of Angels, to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8377:21"/> the generall aſſembly, and Church of the firſt borne, which are written in Heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23.</note> and to God the Iudge of all, and to the Spirits of Iuſt men made perfect, and to Ieſus the Mediator, &amp;c. <hi>O praeclarum illum diem, cùm ad illud animarum conſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium oetum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> proficiſcar,</hi> may the Chriſtian farre better ſay then the Heathen man did! O bleſſed and happy day, when I ſhall goe hence, to bee admitted into the Colledge and Society of all Saints departed this life!<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> Here while we liue below, the good man ſhall haue ſomewhat to vexe his ſoule, as Iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> had by hearing and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in ſo much as he ſhal wiſh ſometimes, <hi>Vtinam aut ego ſurdus, aut ille mutus,</hi> I would either I had no eares to heare, or that man no tongue to ſpeake! But <hi>Foelix Nepotianus,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Hierome, qui haec non videt, haec non audit Nepotian,</hi> is happy, who neither heares, nor ſees theſe things!<note place="margin">Lib. de erat.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> ſhall make the ſenſe full; <hi>Non videbit bello flagrantem Italiam, non ardentem inuidiâ Senatum,</hi> He ſhall not ſee Italy ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with the blood of Patriots, nor the Senate ſweltring in enuy one againſt another, &amp;c. And this is now our deare Maſters condition; his eyes ſhall not ſee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.</note> nor his eares heare that which ſhall wound his ſoule any more; his eyes ſhal no more wound his heart. Should the abomination of deſolation, the Idoll of the Maſſe bee ſet vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the holy place; and <hi>Dagon</hi> ſhoulder the Arke out of doores hereafter, as the Arke hath done <hi>Dagon</hi> heretofore; Happy he, his eyes ſhall not ſee this, <hi>Foelix Nepotianus,</hi> our <hi>Nepotian</hi> is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, that ſhall neither heare, nor ſee any of all this.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:8377:22"/>
            <p>Should ſuch inteſtine iarres begin againe, as once did betweene thoſe two fatall Houſes for the Maſtery of the double Roſe, ſhould we ſee in our owne Land, and of our owne Country-men, Enſigne borne againſt Enſigne, and Croſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Croſſe, <hi>Signa pares aquilas, &amp; pila mina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia pilis, ſoelix Nepotianus hoc non videret, &amp;c.</hi> happy he his eyes ſhould behold none of al this Should <hi>Rabſhakeh, Zenacheribs</hi> Generall, approach our Ports at Sea, raile, and blaſpheme the Hoaſts of the liuing God, with Dog<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Hereticke; tell vs to our teeth, that hee would come vp with the multitude of his Charriots, to the ſides of our <hi>Lebanon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 19 23.</note> and would enter into the Lodgings of our Borders, and into the Forreſt of our <hi>Carmel;</hi> happy hee his eares ſhall be filled with none of theſe blaſphemies; But in ſtead of ſeeing the one, he now ſees the Beatificall face of God, and in ſtead of the other, he heares the noiſe of Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, and the ſongs of Seraphins, <hi>Collectus est à facie itae,</hi> he is taken away from the euill to come; The Orator ſaies, that preſently vpon the death of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſſus</hi> ſuch miſery befell the State of <hi>Rome, Vt mihi non erepta à dijs immortalibus vita, ſed donata mors eſſe videatur;</hi> life was not ſo much taken from him, for a puniſhment, as death beſtowd on him for a reward; Pray God his proue not ſo; pray God his death be not <hi>Primitiae dormientium,</hi> in ſome ſenſe, but a ſay of that mortality, which is feard to follow, I feare it is.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh.</hi> 14.</note>Howſoeuer it be good for him, 'tis ill for vs, he is gone, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as our Sauiour ſaid, to his owne houſe and long home, and hath left vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8377:22"/> ſome of vs without houſe or home, and yet we are not alone neither in our griefes, while the Church and Common-wealth, if I might not ſpeake too broad, the whole Chriſtian world ſhares with vs in his loſſe. For what <hi>Hortenſius</hi> of <hi>Brutus,</hi> we haue double cauſe to grieue <hi>Brutus, quod &amp; ipſe Republicâ careas, &amp; illa Te;</hi> that I of him, the Common-wealth hath a ſhare in this loſſe, For as much as though he want not the Common-wealth now (hee's better prouided for) yet, the Common-wealth will want him! I haue ended that Theame at laſt, though himſelfe be a Theame without end; an immortall Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Pardon my length, griefe keepes no houres; I come in a few words to admoniſh you that be aliue, <hi>Exercitia enim magis ſunt iſta quàm fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera!</hi> Theſe Commemorations be rather exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the vſe of the liuing, then for the honor of the dead, that you labour to flye from the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, the euill to come, and I would I could ſay it were <hi>malum venturum,</hi> an euill to come, and no more: but 'tis preſent, there is euill that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>Malum culpa,</hi> the euill of ſinne, and where this is preſent, you may be ſure, <hi>Malum poe ae,</hi> the euill of puniſhment will not ſtay long behind, <hi>Flagitium &amp; flagellum vt acus &amp; filum,</hi> where ſinne goes before, ſinne and a ſcourge are as the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and the thred, &amp;c. vengeance will limpe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and creepe where it cannot goe.</p>
            <p>The Harueſt of the whole earth is now ready, and Gods Sickle is in his hand to reape downe all;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11.</note> pray then and labour to be deliuered <hi>à prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenti malo ſeculo,</hi> from this preſent euill world.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8377:23"/> Let vs enter into our own hearts, and there eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of vs ſtudy to find the plague of his owne heart,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings</hi> 8.</note> by a ſerious reuiew of our waies paſt, and be wiſe, As <hi>Dauid</hi> askes, How many are the daies of thy Seruant? ſo 'twere good for vs, if with <hi>Dauid</hi> we would oftner aske,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 93.</note> How many are my dayes? how long haue I liued? and how haue I beſtowed theſe daies? For our Rents and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, we haue Rentall Bookes; for our Money, Bags and Cheſts; for our Garments, Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robes and Preſſes; and we know how to ſpend, and vſe thoſe ſparingly, and with moderation; onely we are waſters of our daies, as if wee had <hi>Methuſalems</hi> yeeres in a Treaſure. <hi>Pliny</hi> makes man to complaine of the gods, that the Eagle and Stagge were longer lyu'd then he, and that mans age was nothing; Hee does not well to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine ſo; For, <hi>Non parum habemus temporis, ſed mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum perdimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec. Epiſt.</note> 'Tis not a little time that we liue, but 'tis much time that we loſe. What with <hi>nihil agendo,</hi> and <hi>aliud agendo,</hi> and <hi>male agendo,</hi> with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, or worſe then nothing, wee bring our yeeres to a few minutes. <hi>Infantes ſumus, dum ſenes videmur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martial.</note> we are but Infants, when we looke like old men. Careleſſe men as we are; we ſpend our allowance of lights; in Ryot and Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and ſo at laſt are faine to goe to bed darkling! we dreame of reſt here, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate vpon I know not what <hi>Elizian</hi> Fields, and Ayery Paradiſes vpon earth, whereas God knowes, we haue here nought elſe but <hi>deſideri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quietis,</hi> a deſire to reſt; onely in Heauen, <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etem de ſideriorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> reſt to all our deſires! I ſay, we
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8377:23"/> build to our ſelues Caſtles in the Aire, like <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophanes</hi> Cuckoe in the Clouds! when as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Stulte, hac nocte,</hi> Thou foole,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.</note> this night caſts a dampe vpon all our fleeting, and ſpeculatiue deſignes; In Heauen reſt? Let me ſpeake that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; I ſaid not true, No, not in Heauen reſt, yet: Till the reſurrection of all Fleſh, at the laſt Day!</p>
            <p>For as all the Creation grones on earth (in the Apoſtles Metaphore) longing to bee deliuered from the bondage, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> ſo doe the bleſſed Soules deceaſed, ſigh and grone after their manner, to be re-vnited to their owne bodies, and then they ſhall reſt in that Day. When the Bride-grome is abſent, then men faſt, ſaies our Sauiour; but when preſent, they reſt &amp; reioyce. Our bodies be the Bride-groomes, our Soules the Brides; Till theſe meet againe, they faſt, after reioyce, &amp; reſt. Wonderful ſtrange, (you'le ſay) that a Soule clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with Glory and Immortality, ſhould deſire the company of a Carcaſſe lapt in Lead: <hi>Non be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè conueniunt,</hi> what communion between corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; incorruption? yet ſo 'tis; for, <hi>Quid eſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ille animarum clamor?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iu. Dedic Eccles.</note> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) What meanes the bleating of thoſe innocent Lambes? the cries of Soules in the <hi>Reuelation?</hi> He anſwers, <hi>Clamor</hi> is but <hi>Amor, &amp; magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſiderium,</hi> This cry is but a loue, &amp; longing deſire, to be reioyned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to their owne bodies.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>A labore requieſcunt qui in Domino moriuntur, ſed non requieſcunt interim à clamore,</hi> thoſe bleſſed Soules do reſt from their labour, not from their clamour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Soules of the ſlaughtered bodies, doe yet cry from vnder
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8377:24"/> the Throne of God, and the ſame Father giues the reaſon; <hi>Quia etſi nihil habent, quod moleſtet, nondum tamen habent quod delectet, donec requiem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio, donec Sabbatum, Paſcha ſequatur,</hi> for though they feele nothing to afflict them; yet they haue not all that delights them, till ſuch time as the Reſurrection follow their reſt, and an eternall Sabbath in Heauen, this bitter Paſſeouer on earth; then ſhall they flow in all perfection of Bliſſe, then perfectly taken from euill to come.</p>
            <p>And is that all? No; that's but the one halfe of their bleſſedneſſe; for beſides this ereption and deliuerance from euill, they ſhall be inueſted in the preſent fruition of all good whatſoeuer; here be heard the cries of captiues, and ſicke, and poore, &amp;c. There the captiue ſhall haue his free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the ſicke his health, the poore, riches; the blind, ſight, the lame ſhall be reſtored to his legs; the Orphane to his Parents, the Widdow to her Husband, the ſad man to a neuer-interrupted ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, the old man ſhall haue his youth renewed, the child his age filled, the weake his ſtrength re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, euery valley ſhall be exalted, euery croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thing ſhall bee made ſtraight; when that which is perfect is come,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> then that which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect ſhall be done away; the dead in Chriſt eternall Life freely beſtowed, The gift of God is eternall Life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. In compariſon of this good to come;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.15.</note> all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treaſure is but meere beggery, all the pompe and glory of this earth, but dung and darkeneſſe; all pleaſures whatſoeuer but nauſcous and loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; in a word, All fleſh is graſſe, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8377:24"/> of it as the flowre of that graſſe, not <hi>gramen,</hi> but <hi>foenum,</hi> withered graſſe; withered before it be plucked vp: onely the Word of the Lord, the Kingdome of Heauen promiſed in that Word, endureth for euer; there we may hope to meete all againe, but here on earth neuer. The Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard is ſmitten, and wee the Sheepe of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſhall be ſcattered abroad.</p>
            <p>TO God the Father, which brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20.</note> that great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of the Sheepe, through the blood of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Couenant, make you perfect in euery good worke, working in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt: to whom be glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
